<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><title>Joe Thomas</title><link href="https://jsthomas.github.io/" rel="alternate"></link><link href="https://jsthomas.github.io/feeds/all.atom.xml" rel="self"></link><id>https://jsthomas.github.io/</id><updated>2014-04-02T00:00:00-04:00</updated><entry><title>A Mathematics Geneaology Project Visualizer</title><link href="https://jsthomas.github.io/math-genealogy-visualizer.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2014-04-02T00:00:00-04:00</published><updated>2014-04-02T00:00:00-04:00</updated><author><name>Joe Thomas</name></author><id>tag:jsthomas.github.io,2014-04-02:/math-genealogy-visualizer.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;A program to visualize data from the Mathematics Geneaology Project&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;The
&lt;a href="http://genealogy.math.ndsu.nodak.edu/"&gt;Mathematics Geneaology Project&lt;/a&gt;
(MGP) is a publicly searchable database that records advisor-advisee
relations between mathematicians. Their website is interesting,
particularly if you're interested in the history of
mathematics. Unfortunately, their website is also mostly text-based;
there isn't a way to visualize the relationships between large groups
of people.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I've created a tool that produces a directed graph displaying the
advisor-advisee relations stored in the MGP database. I created this
tool in 2012 in order to learn about how to process data from the web
using python.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Example Output&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;After reading the steps below, you should be able to produce a picture
like the one below.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="A genealogical tree" src="https://jsthomas.github.io/images/mgptree/gauss.png" style="width: 764px; height: auto;"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Naturally, the real purpose of the tool is to make much bigger graphs
than this!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Download&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You will need the following:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A copy of my python script which you can &lt;a href="https://jsthomas.github.io/docs/mgptree/mgptree.zip"&gt;download here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A working python installation with the "requests" package.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;An installation of &lt;a href="http://www.graphviz.org/"&gt;graphviz&lt;/a&gt; (this
program takes care of the actual graph drawing).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Basic knowledge of the command line.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On an Ubuntu machine, these dependencies (&lt;code&gt;graphviz&lt;/code&gt; and &lt;code&gt;requests&lt;/code&gt;)
can be installed via:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="highlight"&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;jthomas@emu:$ sudo apt install pip graphviz
jthomas@emu:$ sudo pip install requests
&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Usage Example&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The easiest way to learn how to use this tool is by way of an
example. Place the &lt;code&gt;mgptree&lt;/code&gt; script in a convenient folder (the
program generates a number of files). Change the permissions on the
script so that you can execute it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Let's say we want to generate a tree for Gauß and Fourier, going back
5 generations. The first step is to prepare a file of names for our
search:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So, we create a unicode text file:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="highlight"&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;Gauß Carl Friedrich
Fourier Jean-Baptiste Joseph
&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I'll call the file &lt;code&gt;gf.txt&lt;/code&gt;. Now we need to get some data from the
web. We do this as follows:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="highlight"&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;jthomas@emu:$ mgptree -g 5 -s -i gf.txt -o gf.mgp
Saved 25 records to file gf.mgp.
&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The &lt;code&gt;-s&lt;/code&gt; option indicates we want to "scrape" data from the MGP
website. The &lt;code&gt;-g&lt;/code&gt; option indicates how many generations backward we
want to search. The &lt;code&gt;-i&lt;/code&gt; denotes our input file, the &lt;code&gt;-o gf.mgp&lt;/code&gt;
indicates that we want to save our results in a database named
&lt;code&gt;gf.mgp&lt;/code&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now we need to graph the data, so we type the following:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="highlight"&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;:: bash

jthomas@emu:$ mgptree -p -i gf.mgp -o gf.dot
jthomas@emu:$ dot -Tpng gf.dot -o gf.png
&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the first line, the &lt;code&gt;-p&lt;/code&gt; indicates we are now in "plotting mode"
where we want to convert the input database &lt;code&gt;gf.mgp&lt;/code&gt; to a textual
format, which we'll save as &lt;code&gt;gf.dot&lt;/code&gt;. The next line hands the textual
data to the graphviz program &lt;code&gt;dot&lt;/code&gt;, which converts it to a PNG image
file named &lt;code&gt;gf.png&lt;/code&gt;. (Many other file formats are available.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="Genealogical trees of Gauss and Fourier" src="https://jsthomas.github.io/images/mgptree/gf.png" style="width: 1915px; height: auto;"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Creating the intermediate database &lt;code&gt;gf.mgp&lt;/code&gt; allows us to work with the
data offline, without having to query the web while we are figuring
out how we want to plot the data.  For example, suppose we only want
to present two generations of the data we just downloaded. Then we'd
type&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="highlight"&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;jthomas@emu:$ mgptree -p -g2 -i gf.mgp -o gf_tiny.dot
jthomas@emu:$ dot -Tpng gf_tiny.dot -o gf_tiny.png
&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;and we wouldn't have to retrieve any information from the web. The
result, &lt;code&gt;gf_tiny.png&lt;/code&gt; looks like this:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="A small genealogical tree of Gauss and Fourier." src="https://jsthomas.github.io/images/mgptree/gf_tiny.png" style="width: 907px; height: auto;"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This feature can be pretty useful if you're trying to work with very
large sets of data and don't know how much information you want to
present.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Usage Tips&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Math Geneaology Project has some "holes" in its data. This seems
to be particularly true for mathematicians who didn't get their degree
in Europe or the US. If you or your advisor aren't listed, add your
data to their website
&lt;a href="http://genealogy.math.ndsu.nodak.edu/submit.php"&gt;here&lt;/a&gt; to help fill
in the gaps!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The number of requests to the MGP's database can grow to be quite
large if you search back 10 or more generations. In particular, it's
probably not a good idea to try to generate a tree for a large number
of people &lt;em&gt;and&lt;/em&gt; many generations.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Accurately matching name data isn't easy. For example, the
mathematician Felix Klein is really named Christian Felix Klein. If
your searches don't succeed, check to make sure you've got your name
data right. This is particularly true for names with accents and
umlauts.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Making Pretty Graphs&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Because my script produces an intermediate &lt;code&gt;.dot&lt;/code&gt; file, it is possible
for you to edit that file to add additional information or decorations
to the graph. Don't like the font I chose? Change the &lt;code&gt;font=Courier&lt;/code&gt;
entry in the &lt;code&gt;.dot&lt;/code&gt; file. Want to adjust a few nodes so that
significant mathematicians have special node colors? Search for their
names in the &lt;code&gt;.dot&lt;/code&gt; file, then add the metadata
&lt;code&gt;color=[your color here]&lt;/code&gt; to their nodes. The documentation for
graphviz is very useful for tasks like this.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Questions, Comments, and Bug Reports&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you end up using this script to do something cool, or want to ask
me some questions about how to use it, or want to report a bug,
&lt;a href="https://jsthomas.github.io/pages/about.html"&gt;here is my contact information&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;</content></entry><entry><title>A Camera-Based Virtual Keyboard System</title><link href="https://jsthomas.github.io/vkeyboard.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2013-12-10T00:00:00-05:00</published><updated>2013-12-10T00:00:00-05:00</updated><author><name>Joe Thomas</name></author><id>tag:jsthomas.github.io,2013-12-10:/vkeyboard.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;A brief summary of my term project for ECE 532&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;In the Fall of 2013, I developed a camera-based keyboard system as my
term project for an image analysis course. This page provides a brief
summary of my project.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In my system, a webcam looks down on a user's hands, which rest on a
paper keyboard template. My program collects images from the webcam to
determine when and where the user touches the keyboard template. When
the user touches a key, my program produces the corresponding letter
as output.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Virtual keyboards are still actively researched in computer science
and electrical engineering. The system I implemented uses techniques
published in [1]-[3] between 2010 and 2013. Camera-based virtual
keyboards require a number of interesting image analysis techniques to
implement. They are particularly of interest in mobile applications
and in areas where one would like to avoid the cost of a physical
keyboard (for example, projects providing computers to people in the
developing world).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1&gt;Processing Steps&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The virtual keyboard system I implemented needed to solve three main
problems:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Detect the locations of the user's fingertips.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Detect whether any fingertips are in contact with the tabletop.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When a fingertip touches the tabletop, determine which key was
pressed on the keyboard.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The first problem can be solved by segmenting an input image &lt;span class="math"&gt;\(I\)&lt;/span&gt; into
two regions: one representing the hands and another representing the
background. For each connected component of the hand region, we can
extract a contour &lt;span class="math"&gt;\(\gamma\)&lt;/span&gt; that traverses the boundary
counterclockwise. Places where &lt;span class="math"&gt;\(\gamma\)&lt;/span&gt; has high curvature (the
places where &lt;span class="math"&gt;\(\gamma\)&lt;/span&gt; bends the most sharply) typically correspond to
fingertips.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="Virtual keyboard processing steps." src="https://jsthomas.github.io/images/vkeyboard/kb_processing.png" style="width: 1680px; height: auto;"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I addressed the second problem using a technique called &lt;em&gt;shadow
analysis&lt;/em&gt;, which is discussed in [1]. With this technique, we perform
another segmentation on &lt;span class="math"&gt;\(I\)&lt;/span&gt;, to locate the regions in the image that
represent the shadows of the user's hands. Then, we examine small
neighborhoods near the user's fingertips. If the proportion of
shadow-pixels in a given neighborhood is above a certain threshold, we
infer that the corresponding fingertip is not in contact with the
tabletop (because it has a shadow). Otherwise, we declare that
fingertip to be touching the keyboard.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The last problem is solved by making some assumptions about the
geometry of the keyboard and imaging system. I assumed that the
keyboard template displays four easily identifiable control points
arranged in a rectangle, and that the front edge of the control
rectangle is parallel to the &lt;span class="math"&gt;\(x\)&lt;/span&gt;-axis of the camera's coordinate
system. With these additional assumptions, it isn't too hard to invert
the perspective projection and recover the keyboard-space coordinates
of each keypress from the image-space coordinates of the fingertips.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1&gt;Results&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;After implementing my virtual keyboard system in python, I analyzed
its performance under different lighting and usage conditions. My
tests suggest that a camera-based user interface that uses shadow
analysis will work best under conditions where one has fine control
over the lighting conditions and the user does not need to enter very
much data at one time. For example, a camera-based user interface
would work well in an interactive museum exhibit, but it might not be
a very good tool for word processing in a dark coffee shop. Currently,
camera-based keyboards cannot provide the speed and accuracy
achievable on physical keyboards (but for that matter, neither do
touchscreen keyboards).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1&gt;Downloads&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Below are links to the paper and code I wrote for the term project. I
used the code within &lt;a href="http://ipython.org/"&gt;ipython&lt;/a&gt; to conduct my
experiments, and used the &lt;a href="http://opencv.org/"&gt;OpenCV&lt;/a&gt; project to get
data from the camera. OpenCV's support for python is still under
development, so if you examine my code you may have to adapt it to
work with your particular hardware and copy of OpenCV.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Paper:
  &lt;a href="https://jsthomas.github.io/docs/vkeyboard/vkeyboard.pdf"&gt;A Camera Based Virtual Keyboard with Touch Detection by Shadow Analysis&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Project Code: &lt;a href="https://jsthomas.github.io/docs/vkeyboard/vkeyboard.zip"&gt;vkeyboard.zip&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;References&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Y. Adajania, J. Gosalia, A. Kanade, H. Mehta, and N. Shekokar. Virtual
keyboard using shadow analysis. In Emerging Trends in Engineering and
Technology (ICETET), 2010 3rd International Conference on, page 163 to
165, 2010.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;E. Posner, N. Starzicki, and E. Katz. A single camera based floating virtual
keyboard with improved touch detection. In Electrical Electronics Engineers
in Israel (IEEEI), 2012 IEEE 27th Convention of, page 1 to 5, 2012.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;M. Hagara and J. Pucik. Fingertip detection for virtual keyboard
based on camera. In Radioelektronika (RADIOELEKTRONIKA), 2013 23rd
International Conference, page 356 to 360, 2013.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;script type="text/javascript"&gt;if (!document.getElementById('mathjaxscript_pelican_#%@#$@#')) {
    var align = "center",
        indent = "0em",
        linebreak = "false";

    if (false) {
        align = (screen.width &lt; 768) ? "left" : align;
        indent = (screen.width &lt; 768) ? "0em" : indent;
        linebreak = (screen.width &lt; 768) ? 'true' : linebreak;
    }

    var mathjaxscript = document.createElement('script');
    mathjaxscript.id = 'mathjaxscript_pelican_#%@#$@#';
    mathjaxscript.type = 'text/javascript';
    mathjaxscript.src = 'https://cdnjs.cloudflare.com/ajax/libs/mathjax/2.7.0/MathJax.js?config=TeX-AMS-MML_HTMLorMML';
    mathjaxscript[(window.opera ? "innerHTML" : "text")] =
        "MathJax.Hub.Config({" +
        "    config: ['MMLorHTML.js']," +
        "    TeX: { extensions: ['AMSmath.js','AMSsymbols.js','noErrors.js','noUndefined.js'], equationNumbers: { autoNumber: 'AMS' } }," +
        "    jax: ['input/TeX','input/MathML','output/HTML-CSS']," +
        "    extensions: ['tex2jax.js','mml2jax.js','MathMenu.js','MathZoom.js']," +
        "    displayAlign: '"+ align +"'," +
        "    displayIndent: '"+ indent +"'," +
        "    showMathMenu: true," +
        "    messageStyle: 'normal'," +
        "    tex2jax: { " +
        "        inlineMath: [ ['\\\\(','\\\\)'] ], " +
        "        displayMath: [ ['$$','$$'] ]," +
        "        processEscapes: true," +
        "        preview: 'TeX'," +
        "    }, " +
        "    'HTML-CSS': { " +
        "        styles: { '.MathJax_Display, .MathJax .mo, .MathJax .mi, .MathJax .mn': {color: 'inherit ! important'} }," +
        "        linebreaks: { automatic: "+ linebreak +", width: '90% container' }," +
        "    }, " +
        "}); " +
        "if ('default' !== 'default') {" +
            "MathJax.Hub.Register.StartupHook('HTML-CSS Jax Ready',function () {" +
                "var VARIANT = MathJax.OutputJax['HTML-CSS'].FONTDATA.VARIANT;" +
                "VARIANT['normal'].fonts.unshift('MathJax_default');" +
                "VARIANT['bold'].fonts.unshift('MathJax_default-bold');" +
                "VARIANT['italic'].fonts.unshift('MathJax_default-italic');" +
                "VARIANT['-tex-mathit'].fonts.unshift('MathJax_default-italic');" +
            "});" +
            "MathJax.Hub.Register.StartupHook('SVG Jax Ready',function () {" +
                "var VARIANT = MathJax.OutputJax.SVG.FONTDATA.VARIANT;" +
                "VARIANT['normal'].fonts.unshift('MathJax_default');" +
                "VARIANT['bold'].fonts.unshift('MathJax_default-bold');" +
                "VARIANT['italic'].fonts.unshift('MathJax_default-italic');" +
                "VARIANT['-tex-mathit'].fonts.unshift('MathJax_default-italic');" +
            "});" +
        "}";
    (document.body || document.getElementsByTagName('head')[0]).appendChild(mathjaxscript);
}
&lt;/script&gt;</content></entry></feed>