<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><title>Joe Thomas - Jobs</title><link href="https://jsthomas.github.io/" rel="alternate"></link><link href="https://jsthomas.github.io/feeds/jobs.atom.xml" rel="self"></link><id>https://jsthomas.github.io/</id><updated>2021-08-17T00:00:00-04:00</updated><entry><title>Thoughts on running a job search in 2021</title><link href="https://jsthomas.github.io/job-search-2021.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2021-08-17T00:00:00-04:00</published><updated>2021-08-17T00:00:00-04:00</updated><author><name>Joe Thomas</name></author><id>tag:jsthomas.github.io,2021-08-17:/job-search-2021.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;Some notes from my most recent job search.&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;I recently wrapped up a job search. My new job starts as I'm in the
process of leaving the &lt;a href="https://www.recurse.com/"&gt;Recurse Center&lt;/a&gt;, so
I thought this would be a good time to summarize my impressions of the
job market for software developers in 2021.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I've encountered a fair amount of advice for software developers who
are just getting out of university, but less advice for developers on
their second or third job. This post is my attempt to fill that gap a
bit and write down some advice to my earlier self. Hopefully it
contains useful suggestions for other job seekers, especially other
Recursers.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Background&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Like many software engineers, I have mixed feelings about how our
industry (specifically, software companies in the US) conduct
interviews. My first few interviews out of university (circa 2010)
were pretty difficult. These consisted of solving "leetcode" style
problems in a panel interview format, where 5-6 older engineers scowl
at you while you work at a whiteboard. Having been both an interviewer
and an interviewee, my impression is that the process is pretty ad-hoc
and varies a lot between companies. As an industry, we just aren't
that scientific about crafting interviews and reviewing the results.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;After talking to a number of experienced developers and reading
comments on Hacker News, I think many software engineers find the
interview process frustratingly artificial, like a sort of "hazing"
ritual. In this viewpoint, the difficulty of interviewing forces
candidates into a "scarcity" mindset where interviews are hard to get,
job offers are even harder to obtain, and unemployment is to be
constantly feared.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;My mission this Summer has been to change my perspective on that. I
don't think that finding a job will ever be "fun" per se. It's always
a bit stressful. But, I didn't want to operate from the basis that
interviewing is to be feared, especially when that feeling is
amplified by sentiments on social media (e.g. Hacker News).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;General Strategy&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Talking to people about their job searches, I observed two
main strategies:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Develop one strong resume and send it out to many companies.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Target a handful of specific companies that fit your interests.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I lean heavily toward the second strategy and applied to 6-10
positions this time. The following criteria narrowed my search quite a
bit:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;I wanted to continue working on analytics/data engineering problems.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The role needed to allow for remote work.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;I wasn't interested in working for a FAANG type company this time
  out; as far as I can tell, interviewing for these roles is quite
  different from interviewing with a startup.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;I wouldn't take a position that I felt had serious negative
  externalities (i.e. cryptocurrency/NFTs, fossil fuels).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The role would ideally involve some amount of functional programming.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In general, I didn't apply to positions unless I met the majority of
the requirements in the job spec. For most positions I prepared a
custom cover letter. I primarily applied to most companies directly
through their website. The main exception to this rule was companies
affiliated with the Recurse Center; for these I applied via RC's
career services program.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Before I started my search, I overhauled my personal website, LinkedIn
page, and resume. My previous job at a smaller, sales-focused company
had a significant advantage: It was much easier to frame my past work
in terms of a benefit to the company's business. Instead of saying &lt;em&gt;"I
set up server X and built technology Y"&lt;/em&gt;, I could write: &lt;em&gt;"I built X
which serves Y percent of all customers and saved Z dollars."&lt;/em&gt; This
was more difficult when I was working in a research role, separated
from users by several degrees. I think my resume was stronger on this
job search than on previous ones, largely because I kept an up to date
"achievement list" in my previous role.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Companies with an Open Source Presence&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This time I applied to more companies that list their source code on
github. For these I followed a somewhat different strategy.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I started by making a list of public repos the company was actively
developing. This can typically be worked out by examining github
activity and (in some cases) presentations from recent conferences. I
downloaded some of these projects to get a sense of how they worked;
this was a helpful test to determine whether I would want to do this
type of work long term. If I found a project with a smallish issue
that I could solve, I prepared a pull request.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This process had a few benefits:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;It helped me learn a little more about the company's code review
  practices.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;A merged PR gave me something to mention in my cover letter, to help
  me stand out from other applicants.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;It allowed me to expand my portfolio of open source work.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This &lt;em&gt;was&lt;/em&gt; a more labor-intensive strategy, but I considered it worth
the effort. In some cases, this technique allowed me to skip over
technical assessments or other "take home" assignments, because the
hiring manager was happy to use the PR I had prepared as a
substitute. In general, this technique seemed to "fast track" my
application when it worked.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Contracting&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;During my job search I also explored the possibility of working as a
contractor. This came about because one of the companies I applied to
wanted to hire me full time but didn't have the funds to do so;
instead they offered me part time work until they could afford bring
me on full time.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Setting up an LLC isn't terribly difficult (perhaps a day worth of
work and $100-600, all in) and gives you the ability to do some
part-time work while looking for a permanent position. This took some
of the pressure off of my job search and helped me feel more confident
that I could support myself while looking for work. My general
impression is that it's easier to get hired as a contractor than as a
full time employee, because neither side is committed for the long
term.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It's probably worth noting that this strategy might not work as well
if you haven't already built up a broad professional network or are
earlier in your career.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Things I could have improved&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Although I'm happy with the outcome of my job search, there are some
things I could have done better.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Most of my mistakes were errors in "timing" my applications. I applied
to a French company in late July and failed to realize many European
companies are completely shut down in August due to vacations. This
meant that even though they were interested in talking to me in
September, any other offers I received would arrive well &lt;em&gt;before&lt;/em&gt; I
could start their interview process.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I decided to stagger my job applications such that the applications I
felt least confident about went out first and the ones I considered
"safe fallbacks" went out last. I thought this was reasonable because
I was writing custom cover letters, at a rate of 1-2 per day. In
retrospect, this approach was suboptimal. It had the effect of making
my job search longer than it needed to be. One of the "safe fallback"
jobs I had applied to had already been filled earlier in the month; it
couldn't have helped me, even though I was a good fit! It would've
been better to just learn that first thing.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I augmented my main job search by using two jobs boards, AngelList and
FunctionalWorks. I didn't get useful leads from either service,
despite having had success with AngelList in the past. I suspect that
because these tools make it easy to apply to lots of jobs at once,
it's very hard to make your resume stand out when you use these
channels.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I spent a lot of time working on leetcode problems. To my surprise,
this didn't actually come up much during my interviews. The firms I
was really interested in asked me for a sample of my open source work
(i.e. links to github) and/or gave me a take-home exercise that was
quite reasonable. There were no tricky algorithm/puzzle questions. I'm
not sure if I will bother with "grinding leetcode" in the future; I'd
much rather just focus on consistently growing my open source
portfolio and let that speak for itself.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Things that went well&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I found that my professional network was very useful this Summer. My
experience has been that networking effects take time to build up, but
they yield information that would be difficult to obtain any other
way. People I met at the Recurse Center offered to connect me with
managers they knew. Conferences I had attended some years ago produced
useful leads on new jobs. Friends from grad school who had startup
experience and other scientific expertise gave me valuable advice
about whether certain jobs would be a good fit.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Previously, I was uncertain about whether having a blog was especially
useful. My website was very helpful on this job search. Multiple
interviewers mentioned reading through my posts and asked me questions
about past projects I had documented. If I had one recommendation for
new software developers, it would be to start keeping a blog
early. Add a technical post every month or two. Github pages makes
this really easy (and it's free). I now feel pretty confident that a
blog is a good way to "make a name for yourself" especially if you're
interested in somewhat niche topics.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Due to the pandemic, the chances of an onsite interview were basically
zero. I knew that I would need to come across well on video so I set
up my home office such that I would be in front of a plain white wall
with a whiteboard. This ensured I could easily talk through a design
if I needed. I wore a dress shirt for all of my interviews;
essentially the same outfit I wore when I worked in an office in
Boston. I'm not sure that this was strictly necessary, but I think it
gave me a small psychological boost and communicated that I was a
reliable professional with a quality home office.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I spent a fair amount of time preparing questions for interviewers,
especially longer on-site interviews. I found that it can be very
helpful to frame questions in a way that's quantitative and does not
contain a value judgement. For example, instead of asking "How stable
is your production environment?" (value judgement, qualitative) I
instead asked "How many times have you been paged in the last 6
months?" (quantitative). This approach yielded more quantitative &lt;em&gt;and&lt;/em&gt;
qualitative data about a company's technology, so that I was better
informed about the day to day experience of working in a particular
role.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The final thing that I did well was to end some interview processes
early, when I identified that the company or manager wasn't a good fit
for me. Some hiring managers were very pushy about knowing my "three
greatest weaknesses" or my past salary. I decided not to deal with
them further after a first interview, which saved everyone time and
effort. I also terminated some interview processes because managers
described business goals that didn't make sense to me. I used the
following test: "How would my former tech leads react if I presented
this proposal to them?" If the answer was "very negatively", I often
reconsidered whether to continue with an interview.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Feedback&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Interviewing is always somewhat stressful. If you're in the midst of a
job search, my main advice is: Hang in there, you'll find a job if
you're persistent and ask the right questions.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you found this post useful (or conversely, think that this advice
is bad), send me an email. My contact information is listed on the
&lt;a href="/"&gt;About&lt;/a&gt; page.&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="Jobs"></category></entry></feed>