<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><title>Joe Thomas - OSS, Projects</title><link href="https://jsthomas.github.io/" rel="alternate"></link><link href="https://jsthomas.github.io/feeds/oss-projects.atom.xml" rel="self"></link><id>https://jsthomas.github.io/</id><updated>2021-10-20T00:00:00-04:00</updated><entry><title>What I learned publishing an open source package</title><link href="https://jsthomas.github.io/first-opam-package.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2021-10-20T00:00:00-04:00</published><updated>2021-10-20T00:00:00-04:00</updated><author><name>Joe Thomas</name></author><id>tag:jsthomas.github.io,2021-10-20:/first-opam-package.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;Today I published my first package on OPAM! You can find &lt;code&gt;tidy_email&lt;/code&gt;
and its sub-libraries (&lt;code&gt;tidy_email_mailgun&lt;/code&gt;, &lt;code&gt;tidy_email_sendgrid&lt;/code&gt;,
and &lt;code&gt;tidy_email_smtp&lt;/code&gt;)
&lt;a href="https://opam.ocaml.org/packages/tidy_email/tidy_email.0.0.1/"&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;. This
wrapped up a goal I wanted to accomplish while at &lt;a href="https://www.recurse.com/"&gt;Recurse
Center&lt;/a&gt;: Writing a simple (but useful) OCaml
library and making it available via &lt;code&gt;opam&lt;/code&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I chose this project …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Today I published my first package on OPAM! You can find &lt;code&gt;tidy_email&lt;/code&gt;
and its sub-libraries (&lt;code&gt;tidy_email_mailgun&lt;/code&gt;, &lt;code&gt;tidy_email_sendgrid&lt;/code&gt;,
and &lt;code&gt;tidy_email_smtp&lt;/code&gt;)
&lt;a href="https://opam.ocaml.org/packages/tidy_email/tidy_email.0.0.1/"&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;. This
wrapped up a goal I wanted to accomplish while at &lt;a href="https://www.recurse.com/"&gt;Recurse
Center&lt;/a&gt;: Writing a simple (but useful) OCaml
library and making it available via &lt;code&gt;opam&lt;/code&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I chose this project for several reasons:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;I wanted more experience designing small APIs in OCaml.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;I thought releasing a small library would help me understand how
"open source maintainer" work differs from paid closed-source
application development.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;I wanted to learn more about the mechanics/process of packaging
   code for OPAM.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The rest of this post explains the process I used and which parts
worked well. Most of this discussion is applicable to general open
source development, but some of the tooling-related points are
specific to OCaml.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1&gt;Picking a Topic&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When I started my batch at RC, I knew that I wanted to publish
&lt;em&gt;something&lt;/em&gt;, but hadn't settled on a topic. Contributing to other
projects was a valuable source of ideas. After working on a couple of
issues for the web framework
&lt;a href="https://github.com/aantron/dream"&gt;Dream&lt;/a&gt;, I wrote a small &lt;a href="https://jsthomas.github.io/ocaml-email.html"&gt;blog
post&lt;/a&gt; showing how to
build a simple email feature with Mailgun. That started a discussion
with other Dream contributors about how to simplify the implementation
of email features.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;After a few more conversations, I decided to write an "adapter"
library that creates a consistent interface across different email
services. Instead of having to study Mailgun or Sendgrid's REST API
and worry about the details of making HTTP requests, you can install
&lt;code&gt;tidy_email&lt;/code&gt;, provide your API keys, and use a &lt;code&gt;send&lt;/code&gt; function that
consumes a simple email type. The library also makes switching email
providers as simple as changing your credentials.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I intentionally kept the scope of the library very small, since this
allowed me to complete the project in a short time frame
while learning several new skills/systems.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1&gt;Looking at "Prior Art"&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Before I started implementing, I researched existing libraries that
dealt with email. This took time but paid dividends by helping me to
avoid re-inventing existing functionality. I learned more about
&lt;a href="https://github.com/oxidizing/letters/"&gt;&lt;code&gt;letters&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/a&gt;, a library for
sending email via SMTP and supporting libraries like
&lt;a href="https://github.com/mirage/mrmime"&gt;&lt;code&gt;mrmime&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/a&gt; for parsing and
generating email. Later, I utilized some of these libraries while
adding an SMTP option to &lt;code&gt;tidy_email&lt;/code&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Investigating other work in the OCaml web development space helped me
to articulate some of the design goals for my library.  I looked at
the web framework
&lt;a href="https://github.com/oxidizing/sihl/tree/master/sihl-email"&gt;sihl&lt;/a&gt;,
which has email among it's many capabilities, and realized I wanted to
make a very "slim" library that didn't couple sending email with other
dependencies related to SQL, HTTP, etc.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1&gt;Picking a Name&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Naming things is hard! I spent some time looking through OPAM to see
which names were already taken (&lt;code&gt;emile&lt;/code&gt;, &lt;code&gt;letters&lt;/code&gt;). Ultimately, I
decided on these constraints:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The name needed to be short, easy to search and remember.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Ideally it would have only simple English words in it.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The name should relate to email in an obvious way.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I settled on &lt;code&gt;tidy_email&lt;/code&gt; based on Dream's description as a "tidy,
feature-complete web framework". The goal of the library would be to
provide a "tidy" (i.e. well-designed, beginner-friendly) API for
sending mail, and hopefully appeal to people who also like Dream.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One mistake I made early on was not sticking to a consistent naming
scheme; I had &lt;code&gt;tidy-email&lt;/code&gt;, &lt;code&gt;tidy_email&lt;/code&gt;, and "tidy email" in
different places. Fortunately, github makes it fairly easy to re-name
a repo if you change your mind later; it will even redirect from the
old repo name to the new one.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1&gt;Writing a First Draft&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Even though &lt;code&gt;tidy_email&lt;/code&gt; is quite simple. It took me some time to set
all the resources up.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Before I could get an account with Sendgrid, I had to register a
domain and create a simple website. I used AWS for this because I was
already familiar with it from past jobs. I also needed to register for
Mailgun and create keys for API and SMTP access. At some point, I had
accumulated enough credentials that I needed to set up password
management to stay organized.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Once I had access to services, I was able to write a first draft of
the library. This turned out to be harder than I expected! I wasted a
lot of time over-complicating my code with new concepts I had learned
(functors and higher order modules). Eventually I came to my senses
and wrote a much simpler implementation.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I found keeping good notes to be quite helpful in this phase. Later, I
turned these notes into documentation explaining how to set up mail
services and some relevant trade-offs when choosing a service (tl;dr:
Mailgun was the easiest, lowest-commitment way to get started).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1&gt;Getting Feedback&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;My main advice is: Don't go it alone. Having someone (ideally a more
experienced maintainer) review early drafts of work was really
valuable for staying on track. This helped me:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Understand how new users would think.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Re-order things to make them easier for first-time users to understand.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Remove confusing or superfluous parts of my API.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Leverage github features I wasn't aware of (actions and secrets).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I also found it helpful to attend &lt;a href="https://discuss.ocaml.org/t/ocaml-cafe-wed-oct-13-1pm-u-s-central/8610"&gt;OCaml
Cafe&lt;/a&gt;
(this is currently meeting on Zoom). A lecture about &lt;code&gt;dune&lt;/code&gt; given by
Rudi Grinberg showed me some techniques that made managing multiple
&lt;code&gt;.opam&lt;/code&gt; files much easier.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1&gt;Testing&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I didn't keep a careful count of my hours but I estimate that more
than half were spent writing unit and integration tests. Setting these
up early made it much easier to iterate on my design and accept pull
requests. Github actions were pretty straightforward to configure
(specified with a simple YAML
&lt;a href="https://github.com/jsthomas/tidy_email/blob/main/.github/workflows/test.yml"&gt;file&lt;/a&gt;)
after looking at a few examples. I appreciated not having to sign up
for yet another service in order to get a simple CI system working.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In &lt;code&gt;tidy_email&lt;/code&gt;, an "integration test" is just a small executable that
tries to send an email to a mailbox. I used github secrets to add API
keys to my project so that integration tests could run securely on an
PR/merge that I made. It would've been nice to be able to run
integration tests on outside PRs automatically, but there isn't really
a way to do that securely.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Integration tests ended up being very advantageous for shaking out
problems that new users are likely to encounter. For example, by
testing with (intentionally) invalid SMTP credentials, I
&lt;a href="https://jsthomas.github.io/smtp-debugging.html"&gt;learned&lt;/a&gt; that Mailgun
can terminate SMTP connections in a way that is hard for &lt;code&gt;colombe&lt;/code&gt; to
handle. Debugging this example gave me some valuable experience
digging into &lt;code&gt;tidy_email&lt;/code&gt;'s dependencies and helped me file a good bug
report to help improve &lt;code&gt;colombe&lt;/code&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1&gt;Documentation&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I spent more time than expected writing documentation. The main lesson
I learned is: &lt;em&gt;Don't bury the lede.&lt;/em&gt; When people look at your repo,
they have limited time. Therefore, the first things you should show
them are&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;A simple, one sentence summary of what the library does.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;A minimal working example (code) illustrating the library in action.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Everything that comes after this introduction should be in the service
of getting the user set up as painlessly as possible. In my case, that
meant adding sign-up links to the relevant services the library
supports. I also provided a brief explanation of the trade-offs when
choosing a service.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;code&gt;tidy_email&lt;/code&gt; is small enough that I didn't write documentation beyond
a readme, comments in the code, and folders of working examples. I
think for a project any larger than this, I would have had to invest
some time thinking about how to generate and host a static site with
documentation (e.g. ReadTheDocs).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1&gt;Release&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Publishing my code on &lt;a href="https://opam.ocaml.org/"&gt;opam&lt;/a&gt; was relatively
painless. To sum up the process:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;I ran &lt;code&gt;dune build&lt;/code&gt; one final time and verified my opam files were
   up to date.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;I created a "tag" for my project (&lt;code&gt;git tag -a 0.0.1 &amp;amp;&amp;amp; git push origin 0.0.1&lt;/code&gt;).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;I ran "opam publish", which created a &lt;a href="https://github.com/ocaml/opam-repository/pull/19816"&gt;pull
   request&lt;/a&gt; on
   &lt;code&gt;ocaml/opam-repository&lt;/code&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;~12 hours later my PR passed CI and was approved.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;About 6 hours after that, my PR was merged and showed up on &lt;code&gt;opam&lt;/code&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;My &lt;a href="https://github.com/ocaml/opam-repository/pull/19634"&gt;first
attempt&lt;/a&gt; at
publishing didn't pass CI because of some simple mistakes I made in my
&lt;code&gt;.opam&lt;/code&gt; files. Fixing these was relatively straightforward after
reading the docs and looking at some other repos for reference.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1&gt;Final Thoughts&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;None of the work involved with releasing &lt;code&gt;tidy_email&lt;/code&gt; was especially
&lt;em&gt;hard&lt;/em&gt;, but there were &lt;em&gt;many&lt;/em&gt; small tasks to understand. Compared to
paid application development work, I found that this project had more
"admin work": signing up for services, configuring things, and writing
prose.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Overall, I found this type of work quite rewarding. It has been fun to
see new people discover and star the repo on Github. The project
motivated me to learn aspects of email that I would not have otherwise
explored. Given how much open source software I use, it feels great
to make a small contribution to the community.&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="OSS, Projects"></category></entry><entry><title>How I Contribute to Open Source Projects</title><link href="https://jsthomas.github.io/oss-how-why.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2021-06-27T00:00:00-04:00</published><updated>2021-06-27T00:00:00-04:00</updated><author><name>Joe Thomas</name></author><id>tag:jsthomas.github.io,2021-06-27:/oss-how-why.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;A short explanation of my open source process.&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Contributing to public projects is one of the most fulfilling aspects
of my software development practice. It allows me to make new
professional connections and gain exposure to challenges I would never
encounter on the job. But it &lt;em&gt;is&lt;/em&gt; effortful, especially after a full
day of paid work. Over time, I've developed (mostly by trial and
error) a process that makes it easier for me to fit open source work
into my schedule and make this extra effort worthwhile.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Earlier in my career I wanted to contribute to public projects but
didn't know how to begin. In this post, I tried to provide a concise
summary of the advice I wish I'd received long ago.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Why contribute?&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Like most engineers, my paid work has been on years-long,
closed-source projects driven by deadlines and business
requirements. In that context, it's normal to build with the most
standard components possible. If your Django app needs flash messages,
you probably want to use the &lt;a href="https://docs.djangoproject.com/en/3.2/ref/contrib/messages/"&gt;messages
framework&lt;/a&gt;,
rather than rolling your own solution; there just isn't much business
value in writing something new. As a result, there are some design
problems you don't get to spend much time thinking about while doing paid
work.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Working on OSS projects lets me to grow my skills beyond boundaries
imposed by business concerns. For instance, working on &lt;a href="https://github.com/aantron/dream/issues/43"&gt;this
issue&lt;/a&gt; let me build a
flash message system for a new web framework,
&lt;a href="https://aantron.github.io/dream/"&gt;Dream&lt;/a&gt;. Within the structure of
that project, I had an opportunity to study how Rails, Django, and
Phoenix implement flash messages. Discussing the merits of these
different approaches with more experienced engineers helped me become
a better designer.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I've also found that OSS projects are an effective way to practice the
investigative skills I use on the first few months of a new job. When
I join an organization, I have to get up to speed on new codebases
(sometimes in a language I haven't used before).  Working on an
unfamiliar open source project simulates these conditions, without the
accompanying pressures of a new job.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;How do I find new projects to work on?&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Conferences focused on a specific programming language or family of
technologies are a great way to meet maintainers. When I attended
&lt;a href="http://www.composeconference.org/2017/"&gt;Compose 2017&lt;/a&gt;, a
serendipitous conversation in between sessions led to a 3-4 month
period of making contributions to
&lt;a href="https://github.com/ocsigen/lwt/"&gt;lwt&lt;/a&gt;, learning a lot more about
OCaml, and this &lt;a href="https://jsthomas.github.io/map-comparison.html"&gt;blog
post&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Conferences &lt;em&gt;can&lt;/em&gt; be a bit of a gamble. The costs of travel, lodging,
and fees are significant. Most conferences will post their talks
later. Watching these is a great way to stay informed. This Strange
Loop &lt;a href="https://youtu.be/gCWtkvDQ2ZI"&gt;talk&lt;/a&gt;, for instance, gave me a
good overview of the Unison programming language, which eventually
allowed me to contribute this
&lt;a href="https://github.com/unisonweb/unison/pull/1639"&gt;change&lt;/a&gt;. This approach
is much more efficient for finding projects that spark your interest,
since you can watch talks at 2x speed and skip ones that aren't
useful.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Evaluating whether a project is a good fit&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Once I've found a project (usually on github) that I think is
interesting, there are a few things I check before deciding whether to
contribute.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;First, I look at whether the project has recent commits. If the most
recent commit is more than a few months old, that might mean the
project is abandoned. Since I'm interested in being a contributor
rather than a maintainer, working on these repos is usually not a good
use of time.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The second thing I look at are the project's pull requests. If there
are many old, open pull requests (ones that don't have any comments),
this is another sign that the project might be abandoned. Looking
through closed PRs, or PRs with a lot of comments, typically gives me
some idea of how contributors and maintainers interact. The
maintainers I've interacted with have been friendly and welcoming; I
avoid projects where that isn't the norm.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Next, I'll take a look at the project's issue list. If users and
maintainers write clearly, it's much easier for me to make progress on
an issue without having to ask too many questions. Issues with links
to relevant code, minimal working examples, and repro steps are all
good signs.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I also look to see whether the project has Travis or Circle CI set up,
since that means I can get quick feedback on a PR without talking to
anyone. The CI systems is also helpful as a model for setting up my
development environment; often I will look through the CI
configuration in order to run my unit tests with the exact same
databases/dependencies/settings.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Finally, I'll take a more in-depth look at the codebase itself. At
this point, I'm just trying to answer basic questions, like:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;How is the source tree organized?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Do most of the functions/classes/modules have comprehensible names?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Where are the tests? Where would I add new tests?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Are there comments?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Finding a task&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Once I'm confident that I want to participate, my next step is to
choose an open issue to work on. Ones that are marked "good first
issue" or "beginner" are great for a first contribution, and I'll
often start with those.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I try to keep the scope of my first contribution small. For example,
&lt;a href="https://github.com/arenadotio/pgx/issues/97"&gt;this issue&lt;/a&gt; on the OCaml
library &lt;code&gt;pgx&lt;/code&gt; asked for someone to add support for a different
date-time library (in this case &lt;code&gt;ptime&lt;/code&gt;) because not everyone can use
Jane Street's &lt;code&gt;Core&lt;/code&gt; library. This was an ideal first issue because I
could use the existing &lt;code&gt;Core&lt;/code&gt; implementation as a model for what I
needed to build.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If an issue is a little bit old, it's a good idea to leave a note
asking whether the maintainer is still interested in having it
addressed. For example, I was interested in working on this
&lt;a href="https://github.com/aantron/dream/issues/43"&gt;issue&lt;/a&gt;, but it was a
month old. Rather than jumping into an implementation that might go to
waste, I left a comment expressing interest and offering some design
ideas. Replies in that thread allowed me to create this &lt;a href="https://github.com/aantron/dream/pull/62"&gt;pull
request&lt;/a&gt;, confident in the
knowledge that someone would want to use my work.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Once I've picked out task, it's (finally) time to implement a
solution. If I can get as far as implementing some unit tests and
getting most of them to pass, I post a comment on the issue indicating
that I'm working on a pull request. Personally, I consider it best
practice to &lt;em&gt;only&lt;/em&gt; post one of these comments if I'm very confident
that I'll have a PR ready in the next few days. Conversely, no-one
wants to duplicate effort, so it's courteous to indicate that you're
preparing a PR.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Pull request and review&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Since pull requests take time to review, I try to perform at least one
round of self-review before opening a PR. Generally, I won't open a PR
unless I have fairly good test coverage for my work and the tests (and
lint steps) are passing. At a paid position, it's easy to have a
meeting or use slack to discuss a change. Public projects tend to be
more asynchronous, so it's important to read instructions carefully,
write clearly, and address obvious issues on your own.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When I write a description for my PR, I include a link to the issue it
addresses, usually in the first sentence. If the change adds new types
or functions, I include a summary of that as well. If there are design
details I'm unsure of, I flag these with comments so that the
reviewer(s) can discuss them with me.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The code review process on a public project can be a little different
from code review inside a company. At some jobs, I've observed an
unspoken rule that PRs need to be more or less correct on the first or
second try, otherwise you'll be considered ineffective. My sense is
that the review process on public projects is much more
iterative. Sometimes it isn't possible to gather all of the necessary
requirements until a first PR is drafted and people have something to
react to. It can take several rounds of revision before all of the
interested parties agree that the design is right.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This &lt;a href="https://github.com/aantron/dream/pull/62"&gt;PR&lt;/a&gt; for instance,
required several tries to find a flash message implementation that fit
with the philosophy of the project. These situations are an
opportunity to practice discussing (and justifying) your design
decisions with other technical-minded people. I think the key to
success with public reviews is to read reviewer's comments carefully,
make an effort to understand their goals, and then fit your changes to
support those goals.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;General suggestions&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you plan on making OSS contributions long term, I'd suggest having
both a schedule and dedicated hardware for your work. Working after
dinner from 6 to 8 PM weeknights helps me get into a productive
mindset quickly. Time-boxing my work also helps me avoid exhausting my
interest in a project by putting in too many consecutive hours. Using
an inexpensive, second-hand laptop for my public projects makes it
easy for me to suspend my work when I'm done for the night and then
start the next day exactly where I left off, without having to set up
my browser/editor/terminals again.&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="OSS, Projects"></category></entry></feed>